A Guide to the James and John Booker Collection
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Manuscripts
  - James Booker, [n.p.], letter to Chloe Unity Blair, with an inclusion by A. Blair, 1861 July 14; ALS 4 p.
    Optimistic at the beginning of the war, James Booker praises the "elegant water," "beautiful young Ladies," and "most beautiful country" he finds at the 38th's camp at Winchester. But he notes that one member of the regiment accidentally shot another member from his hometown and now feel terrible. He warns that "cowardly boys" who are avoiding service should beware, since they are likely to be drafted or made to put up breastworks. After salutations and greetings, James indicates where letters should be sent. A. Blair, a relative of James' and possibly Chloe Blair's brother, writes a short note to be included. Blair indicates that he is including a letter that "brother William" received from "brother," who was expecting to go to Manassas. Blair finishes by saying that all are well.
  - James Booker, [n.p.], letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1861 September 6; ALS 3 p.
    James Booker complains of not hearing from his family. He mentions being too ill to serve and that he, consequently, works in the hospital. He talks about patients suffering from jaundice and yellow fever and mentions the poor health of James May, Hugh Norton and Josiah Burnett, as well as the death of Billy Pruett from eating "too much beef liver." In spite of their complaints, he notes that the health of the men in camp is improving. He alludes to having received bad news from Texas, and then states that he will probably not come home as long as he is healthy or until peace is declared. The postscript states that James will try to send for things via any returning soldiers.
  - James Booker, Manassas Junction, Virginia, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1861 October 8; ALS 2 p.
    James Booker reports that his company is healthier than it has been for some time. He has heard about fighting at Falls Church the day before, and reports a conversation with a man from the Danville Grays, who told him that the Yankees are within four miles of his company at Fairfax Court House. From this information, James Booker predicts that a "hard battle" will soon take place. He mentions getting a letter from Addie (perhaps Drury Addison Blair), whose condition is improving.
  - James Booker, Manassas Junction, Virginia, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1861 December 15; ALS 3p.
    This letter is a reply to one or more letters that James had received from his cousin and "sweethearts" a few days earlier. He has just heard that his regiment is about to move into their winter quarters in Gainesville. He will join it when the winter quarters are ready. Meanwhile, the work in his current quarters is lighter and the pay better. He believes the fighting in Centreville will not continue past winter. He mentions meeting a man who had been captured by the Union and who was recently released. According to this man, there are 60,000 sick Yankees in Washington. He also adds that he has heard that two men in Centreville were shot for trying to kill their commanding officer. James closes the letter by asking to be remembered to cousin Eliza Ann Williams and to all the "ladies" at Christmas time.
  - John Booker, Camp Smith, near Manassas, Virginia, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1862 February 19; ALS 3 p.
    Writing from the company's winter quarters near the battlefield of First Manassas, John Booker describes his brother James' sickness, which has left him weak and without an appetite. Other soldiers, including Nathaniel Robertson and Neal Gilbert, have struggled with illness; one, Josiah Burnett, has died. Booker ends his letter by expressing his pleasure at having received his cousin Unity's letter and apologizing that his brother James was unable to write.
  - James Booker, in Greaner Hospital, Richmond, Virginia, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1862 March 15; ALS 3 p.
    James Booker explains why he has been so long in answering Unity's latest letters, stating that he has been in hospital, too ill to write. He had hoped to come home on furlough, but has been separated from his regiment and could not obtain leave. He asks that Unity write to him with the location of his regiment. He also complains about the quality of the food and mentions seeing many acquaintances on their way to the front. He closes by asking his cousin to direct her replies to Greaner's Hospital, care of Surgeon R. G. Banks.
  - James Booker, Camp near Yorktown, Virginia, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1862 April 19; ALS 2p.
    James Booker writes to inform his cousin of the location of his regiment. He indicates that they have been shot at but infrequently hit. He mentions that a man named Tucker, who was wounded in the chin, was the only man from his regiment (he was attached to Captain Carter's Company F) to have been shot. He also notes that many men, mainly Yankees, were killed at last Wednesday's battle and that this evening the Yankees flew a truce flag in order to safely bury their dead. He feels that, because the best of both armies are here, the war will be settled here. He closes by asking that Unity write soon, and direct her letters to him at Yorktown. He also asks her to notify "sister Mary" that Pickney has not yet arrived.
  - John Booker, a camp near Yorktown, Virginia, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1862 April 29; ALS 2 p.
    John Booker describes a new posting and notes that, since leaving the Orange Court House, the troops are living without tents. They stay in the entrenchments every other day and night, and are under constant bombardment by the Yankees. He mentions that there is a good deal of sickness and many are being wounded. Also, he notes that they have elected officers for the next two years. John closes by asking Unity to direct her letter to him at Yorktown.
  - James and John Booker, [n.p.], letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1862 August 3; ALS 4 p.
    James begins by apologizing for the tardiness of his letter: he explains that he has been ill. He then discusses the practice of substitution (arranging for a replacement in the army), concluding that it is having a bad effect on the Confederate Army. He also discusses his work assignment and his health. In a separate letter on the same paper, John tells his cousin about his cold and sore throat. He also states that there is currently no fighting, but he can hear the Yankees firing cannonade "down on the river."
  - James Booker, camp near Hopewell Church, near Winchester, Virginia, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1862 September 30; ALS 2 p.
    James Booker writes that he and his brother John are in good health. They have been marching hard but usually have not gotten enough to eat. Booker reports that the general feeling in the camp is that peace will come soon. Four sick conscripts have arrived (and are named). James complains of having to march in wet clothing after crossing bridge-less streams. He also notes that the sick and wounded have been ordered from Winchester to Staunton and thinks that everyone else will be going to Richmond soon. James looks forward to going there since he has not heard from home since leaving Richmond. He greets other family members and mentions that John will write soon.
  - James Booker, near Winchester, Virginia, letter to cousin, Chloe Unity Blair, 1862 October 17; ALS 2 p.
    Claiming that he would be able to "stand" being a soldier if he received enough to eat, James Booker notes that recently the supply of food has been adequate, but that the men have not gotten enough salt. James Booker notes the illnesses of two men in camp, Bage Pritchett and John Hundley. He compares the entrepreneurship of the Yankees with the more whimsical quality of the Quakers' mercantilism and notes the use of Confederate money and specie to buy provisions. He also describes a month-long religious revival meeting underway in camp.
  - James Booker, Spottsyvania, Virginia, near Fredricksburg, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1862 November 24; ALS 2 p.
    After reporting that he and his brother John are well, James Booker writes that the company has been marching for the past four days and has finally arrived at its camp near Fredericksburg. Many Union soldiers are nearby, and he predicts that the Union troops will soon begin shelling the Confederates. He expects a "hard" battle to commence soon.
  - James Booker, a camp near Culpeper Court House, Culpeper, Virginia, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1863 June 14; ALS 4 p.
    Writing on the Sabbath, James Booker tells his cousin that both he and his brother are well. The members of Company D marched for the past ten days, and they expect to march again the next day, since they are following the movements of the Union troops. A few days previously, the Union had surprised the Confederate cavalry, but the Confederates managed to drive their enemies across the river and take several hundred prisoners. Complaining that "the Yankees is getting too mean to live," James Booker writes that they steal and destroy Southern property, such as meat, corn, and horses. He notes, "I still live in hope of peace soon though I may not live to see it." He observes that at a "very interesting" camp meeting several men, including Captain Herndon, were converted.
  - James Booker, Chambersburg, Pennsylvania, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1863 June 30; ALS 4 p.
    James Booker reports that he and his brother John are well. He mentions that local residents seem fearful of the army and that General Robert E. Lee has ordered his troops to respect private property. He describes the flourishing condition of Pennsylvania farms, noting that this part of the country has not yet felt the effects of the war. James perceives disunity in the people's attitude toward the war, comments on the abolitionists' motives, and mentions that he is boarding at a private house for free in return for guarding the owner's property. He closes by asking that Unity write soon, for he the last letter he received was dated the 13th.
  - James Booker, a camp in Williamsport, Maryland, letter to cousin, Chloe Unity Blair, 1863 July 11; ALS 4 p.
    Writing a few days after Gettysburg, James Booker describes the heavy losses suffered by his division during Pickett's Charge; most of the regiment's officers and many of the enlisted men were killed, wounded, or captured during the assault. James and John Booker escaped harm, though they were nearly taken prisoner by the Union forces. His division has been assigned to escort 5000-6000 Union prisoners to the South. He reports hearing daily of small battles and expects another major battle imminently, although he does not expect his division to be involved because it is on guard in Williamsport, a city where most of the citizens appear to favor the North.
  - John Booker with inclusion from James Booker, Petersburg, Virginia, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1863 September 27; ALS 4 p.
    John Booker writes that he is happy that Chloe enjoyed the revival meeting at Hermon (perhaps the Mount Hermon Baptist Church near Danville), then notes that there is "good preaching" at the camp. He contends that "the prosspect for peece is very gloomy now," given that both sides are preparing for war with more intensity than ever. He reports that, despite rumors, Pickett's division will remain in Virginia. The troops are elated at this news, even though they have little more to do than guard camp and drill three times a day. In a postscript, James Booker asks Chloe Unity Blair to send his letter to his sister soon.
  - James Booker, encampment of the 38th Regiment, near Petersburg, Virginia, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1863 October 4; ALS 4 p.
    Apparently upset that he did not receive a furlough, James Booker wishes for the warmth and comforts of home, writing, "there is none of them that knows how to appreciate a blessing until they are deprived of it." Still, he admits, in wartime he should find satisfaction simply in having enough to eat and enjoying good health; but he cannot be satisfied when speculators sell food to women and children at inflated prices. He observes that the married soldiers have sent for their wives and were boarding them at the homes of local citizens. He observes that General Corse's Brigade had been at the camp near Petersburg, but that they were sent to Tennessee. He also mentions writing to his sister Mary, telling her that he did not need clothing, as he received the box that "you all" sent him. The letter closes with a one-page postscript stating that John made a potato pie, and Cousin Tom ate with the two of them. He sends his regards to Cousin Pollie Ann and mentions that Cousin William Blair and Luther are stationed nearby but will be leaving for Chatanooga, Tennessee, within the next two days. He closes asking for Unity to return his "soldier likeness" to him so he can exchange it for a new one.
  - John Booker, Kinston, North Carolina, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1863 December 22; ALS 3 p.
    After observing that letters from home bring him great pleasure, John Booker chastises his cousin for not writing sooner. He notes that "Flem" Gregory has been ill, but is recuperating. Then he launches into a complaint that energizes the letter: Captain John Herndon is too "lazy" to grant the soldiers in his company furloughs, even though it is Christmas time, and even though the men are not doing anything, not even picket duty. So discontented are the soldiers that many say they will not re-enlist. John Booker claims that he opposes desertion, but that the wealthier men who paid substitutes to serve in the army should have to join, while veteran soldiers should receive furloughs. Angered at the inequality, John exclaims, "this is a rich mans war an a poor mans fight." He ends his letter by observing that Memory Inman, another member of the D Company, is heading home to get married.
  - James Booker, a camp near Kinston, N.C., letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1864 January 1; ALS 4 p.
    Booker reports that although his regiment had begun to march to meet the Yankees in battle, the Union had attacked --and been defeated by --another group of Confederate soldiers thirty-five miles away. He reports that the winter has been fairly pleasant and that food is cheap and plentiful. Despite such abundance, he notes, soldiers have been stealing food from local residents. He mentions a serious theft of $18,000 from the Quarter Master; soldiers are suspected of the deed. James expresses concern over General Barton's attitude towards the Regiment. (Barton has said his men come from "rags and thieves.") James complains that after three years of service he has still not received a furlough. He closes the letter with a stanza from "Amazing Grace."
  - John Booker, [n.p.], letter to cousin, Chloe Unity Blair, 1864 March 1; ALS 2 p.
    John Booker describes the attempt by Virginia Governor William "Extra Billy" Smith and Colonel [Joseph Robert] Cabell to make the men of the 38th Regiment re-enlist. He deplores the strategies they used: calling the men to stand before the "Colors," declaring that any man who wanted to be a slave to the enemy should not re-enlist. John fears that his leaders want to continue to fight at all costs, rather than press for peace; and as long as men re-enlist the war will go on. John also expresses his dissatisfaction with the administration of the Regiment: only the men who re-enlist are granted furloughs, and John has still not received the furlough owed to him in 1862. He mentions that the two new recrutes to Company D are receiving their furloughs ahead of him. Changing the subject, John writes of nearby Union activity and says that they have been expecting a raid. Finally, he writes of Memory Inman's court martial and Captain John Herndon's marriage. He closes the letter by apologizing for its angry tone, writing, "I have bin mad all day."
  - James Booker, Camp near Richmond, Virginia, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1864 March 16; ALS 4 p.
    James Booker informs his cousin of his and his brother's good health. He discusses the treatment of prisoners of war, the unavailability of certain types of foodstuffs and the deprivations of civilians due to the war. He further comments on the weather and his coming duty in the field. He laments the lack of correspondence from home and closes his correspondence with salutations and wishes for his family's good health He apologizes for his poor writing, attributing it to having to finish the letter by firelight.
  - James Booker, 38th Virginia Infantry Camp, letter to Chloe Unity Blair, 1864 April 29; ALS 4 p.
    James Booker replies to Unity's letters of the 17th and 24th. He mentions that his company has been fishing about 20 miles away and that the Yankees are getting closer and are expected to drive the men out of the fishery. He states that the Yankees are believed to be heading for Richmond. James hopes that "this cruel war" may end soon and "in our favor." He closes with a quotation from 1 John. The postscript, written on April 30th, states that the rumor that the Yankees are coming may be false.